hello welcome back it's the fourth
applied active inference Symposium day
two part two on November 14th
2024 we're kicking off this session in
the darkness of the preon on the west
coast appropriately with Maron Hussein
Zade
bagani ml Dawn brain in-the-dark design
principles for the neuromatic inference
under the free energy principle so thank
you Maron for joining looking forward to
your
presentation thank you very much it's a
pleasure to be here
um so today I'm going to be talking
about uh the design principles for
neuromatic inference under the free
energy principle namely the methods that
are inspired by the brain um in order to
model human
perception um just um want to preface
this by saying that this is a
collaboration with my colleague Simon
orbas from Manu University and Professor
friston from UCL and this work has
recently been accepted at the neuro AI
workshop at neurs
2024 so let's just get
started the content is going to be as
follows we're going to be talking about
first the motivation behind this work
why we got started started with this
idea anyway to to introduce the design
principles particularly for these models
and then I'm going to do a quick
refresher on the math side just so we
all get comfortable with the you know
the upcoming derivations that I'm going
to be uh expanding on which covers the
math behind free the free energy
principle particularly a variational
free
energy then I'll do a brief discussion
on what free energy principle is I'm
presume Knows by now because we we' had
so many talks uh since uh the beginning
of the Symposium but I'm going to do a
quick run at that then we'll be talking
about the beian brain hypothesis that
furnishes the foundation for the idea of
modeling human perception as a kind of
inference namely basan inference next we
dive into dejos between the generative
model and a generative process what do
we mean by each one of them knowing the
distinction is crucial for understanding
the free energy principle because Fe
lies on this um notion that there is a
boundary that separates an entity from
uh the environment and separating uh
basically my internal state from the
external State beyond my marov blanket
next we'll talk about variational free
energy and how it's driven how it's
derived basically and then we jump into
the design principles in terms of the
experiments not the things that you need
to consider the things that you need to
Define and how you should go about doing
that in order to model human perception
as a kind of online inference
problem we'll go through some final
thoughts some lessons learned and then
I'll introduce some of the resources for
those of you who are interested in uh
you know pursuing free energy principle
more seriously and delving into the
theory and the Practical side of it and
then we're going to wrap it up with uh a
demonstration um using the GitHub
repository that that is publicly
available by um by by the way
so the motivation is this so you said
deep learning has revolutionized
artificial intelligence um because it
has automated the process of feature
extraction from raw data however it
actually faces a lot of problems for for
example lack of outof distribution
generalizability catastrophic forgetting
and poor interpretability it is known as
a black box basically and the
catastrophic forgetting is basically
when the new knowledge overwrites the
previous knowledge the weights are
getting overwritten so while the network
learns the concept of a cat it might
momentarily forget the concept of a dog
because the paths are shared between
different Concepts that are to be
learned you see in contrast to deep
learning biological neural networks in
your brain and a my brain they do not
suffer from these issues and this
inspires the AI researchers to actually
explore this interesting and intriguing
area called The neuromatic Deep learning
that is all about replicating the brain
mechanisms namely the neuronal message
passing and belief updating within the
AI models purely sprayed by our best
knowledge about how the brain works um a
foundational theory for this approach is
the free energy principle um Fe which
unfortunately despite its potential is
often considered too complex to
understand and to implement an AI simply
because one would need a myriad of
disciplines um under their belt
knowledge about disciplines under their
belt to be able to understand the free
and principle namely you need to know
things for example about dynamical
systems random
processes you need to know about basian
mechanics some Neuroscience some maybe
computational neuroscience and so on and
so forth so as a as a result it's not
it's an intimidating topic let's say for
anybody who wants to just get started
with it so we seek to demystify FP and
basically provide a comprehensive
framework for Designing neuromatic
models within well where we are actually
trying to mimic humanlike perception
capabilities um so here we present a
road map for implementing these models
and by the way a pytorch code repository
for applying FP in a predictive coding
network is going to be introduced here
the link is here that that's a code it's
publicly available and also as I said
the paper will soon be available um by
the neuro AI Workshop um and so
hopefully you guys will have a chance to
take a look at that as
well now let's get started with the ref
refresher of the math so first foremost
the idea of a PDF so it it's an acronym
for a probability density function which
is a function that describes the
likelihood of a continuous random
variable taking on a particular value it
has two conditions it has to be positive
so for a given parameter theta0 for
example the mean of a gaan let's say for
any input X it's always positive and
second we have this normalizer uh sort
of condition that if you integrate a PDF
across the support space of of the input
name the all possible values of X you
will inevitably must receive get to the
actual value of one what this means is
the probability of X the
input getting any value in a in any
range within its support is always one
which means that X will always fall in
in a range in that in its own accepted
range of values so that's 100% so you
need these two if you want to have a
PDF next is the idea of an expectation I
just want to remind you that the reason
I'm going through this math is because
later on when I introduced the steps of
deriving um you know variational free
energy these concepts are absolutely
crucial so hopefully um I'm not going
too fast but um yeah just bear that in
mind that these are very important and
for those of you who are you know math
Savvy and these are two Basics my
apologies now the idea of expectation is
actually the weighted average of all the
possible values that the variable
consume weighted by their probability so
you have the in the first line um the
expected value of x over the probability
distribution the PDF PX so as you notice
we're integrating all possible values of
X multiplied by or weighted by their
corresponding
probability and it's important to note
that you don't you're not limited to you
know calculating the um the expected
value with respect to a variable but you
can also do this exactly the same thing
with a function so the expected value of
function is again the same thing but you
are summing up a weight you're basically
calculating a weighted average of a
function where the weights are the
probability of the input to that
function which is
X now some key Pro probability
components here now we have this idea of
a joint
probability um so a joint distribution
between two variable X X and Y you can
divide it up between like like some
conditional term which is the
probability of x given y multipli by the
probability of Y in the first place or
you can go the other way around the
probability of Y given x times the
probability of X you notice that if X
and Y are independent this conditional
term reduces to probability of X or this
conditional term would reduce the
probability of Y so either way on both
sides you're going to have the
probability of x given y um if X and Y
are indeed
independent next if want to move from a
joint distribution to a marginalized
distribution where you're actually
marginalizing one of the variables out
this is how you can do it so in this
case if you integrate P of XY across all
possible possible values of X in other
words like you literally break this down
and you know basically write it down in
in this you know um constituent terms if
you do this integration you're inev what
basically what you're doing is you're
getting rid of X and then you end up
with a term with a probability
distribution that is only a function of
um
Y and that's what you call a
marginalized probability distribution or
PDF again this is key where will this
come in handy it's going to come in
handy when when I'm going to be talking
about the basium brain hypothesis and
base Rule and so on and so forth so keep
these two equations in mind
please now some properties of logarithms
so this is basically just the definition
of a log so log of a with base b equals
c the definition says that it just means
a equals B to the power C right so for
example the log of 8 base 2 equals 3
because 2 to^ 3 is 8 so the log of
multiplication is some of the logs of
individual terms the log of a division
is the subtraction of individual log
terms that log of denominator minus the
log of the
denominator um the log of a fraction is
literally minus the log of the swapped
fraction literally swap b and a together
from like you know you end up with just
a negative of the of the new loog
term um the power law the log of B to
the power C so basically C drops down as
a coefficient so you end up with this
term C * log of B with base a log of a
with base a if the value
and the base are both the same you end
up with value one and by extension if
you have this term C drops down as a
coefficient and this term equals one so
you end up with C log of one with any
base is always equal to zero why because
a whatever it is to the power zero is
one and last but not least this one is
again very
important Ln of a is basically just a
logarithm a logarithm with you know
where the Bas is natural number e or
it's called the natural log and E is
basically the oiler Oiler number so you
got log of a with base e it's called
just the natural log so when in in
Python when you say numpy do log is
basically the natural
log now the free energy
principle it is a theoretical framework
in Neuroscience it's been developed by
Carl friston
so basically things that persist over
time especially living systems look as
if they are minimizing a certain
quantity it's called free energy it is
as if they're uh sort of maintaining
this boundary that is called a mark of
blanket to persist in the face of random
fluctuations in the uh in the
environment um and this really connects
well with the beian brain hypothesis you
as you will see shortly
so the brain from the perspective of
beian brain
hypothesis it's actually in the game of
inferring the hidden causes behind its
Sensations so namely if you have if you
let's say y to denote the sensations and
X as the hidden State and then this
inference basically means that given my
observation why I want to estimate the
probability distribution over
X right it's basically called a
posterior probability which means that
after having seen an
observation um what is causing in the
world beyond my Markov blanket this
particular sensation or
observation inevitably this requires
having a generative model GM of the
world and this actually connects really
well with Helm hold's um concept of
unconscious inference and it is defined
like that perception is kind of
unconscious inference which means that
we are in the game of you know inferring
the hidden cause behind our our
Sensations for example right now you're
looking at the Monitor and the photons
but the light is hitting the your
sensory epithelia on your eyes those
excitations those those hits those are
your sensation and when you realize that
I'm I'm watching this presentation at at
at active inference Institute um and
this guy is talking his name is mean
this is the slide of a of a face Helm
holes pictures here these are the
inferences that your brain is making
given that particular Sensation that is
hitting the the neurons on the surface
of your eyes right so it's estimating
this probability distribution about
what's happening beyond your markup
blanket now let's talk about the idea of
generative model versus generative
process this is actually very very
important on the right hand side you see
this IDE this generative model as a box
and it has some internal States let's
call them hidden
States this represents the neuronal
activities in your brain um the
excitabilities
um different you know the the voltage
the voltage level let's say of your
neurons that are keep changing all the
time they fluctuate all the
time and these guys I BAS basically
holding information about what's
happening beyond your Markov blanket
right remember what's happening beyond
your Markov blanket is out of your reach
you have absolutely no way of observing
exactly what's happening
right and here we have the generative
process where xstar denotes the actual
things that are happening in the world
which are completely out of reach to you
now if you imagine here you have the
face of a person let's say steep job is
standing in front of me but this is no
like I'm I'm not going to see the truth
what I'm going to see is some sort of a
um a map some sort of a noisy
transformation of the truth xstar right
let's call it why this is what I'm going
to be experiencing this is what's going
to hit and uh induce excitation at my
sensory epithelia on my eyes and then if
you want to look at like um basically
dig deep into the idea of perception as
um unconscious inference the G the game
is this your brain the generative model
in your brain predicts a sensation like
I'm expecting this sensation to be felt
or received at my sensory epithelia on
my Markov blanket and then the actual
sensation why is received so the
difference between the actual sensation
and my prediction is called the
prediction error so using that
prediction error I will update my G
model about the world namely I will
update my belief about what's happening
in the world so this is where my
internal States will change to reflect a
better image of the unknown World beyond
my markof blanket or the parameters of
my generative model are going to
change um to again do a better estimate
of what's happening in the world so that
I will have a better prediction about
the sensations that that world is going
to cause right so generative process
again is not directly
observable and the internal uh States X
this is very important carry information
about the invisible external States xar
beyond my mark of blanket this is where
this connects to the IDE the discipline
of information Theory this is a very
important link by the
way so the generative model what do we
mean by that mathematically speaking now
in a dynamical world a generative model
has belief about the Dynamics of the
world what it means is how fast is the
world changing for example or how is it
changing now if the world is at a given
State X right what does its Dynamics
look like for example it's velocity or
acceleration or even higher temporal
derivatives are like jerk basically all
sorts of rates of changes the rates of
change about the world that's what what
I mean by Dynamics so in a generative
model your generative model will have an
understanding has to have a belief about
how the world is changing Beyond a smart
C blanket so in other words if I'm in
the game of estimating the Dynamics of
the world it means I'm chasing a moving
Target what it means is at any given
time when I want to infer what's
happening in the world by the time I've
made that inference the world has
already moved so that basically makes
inference uh a tricky task especially if
I'm in a in a you know highly dynamical
World it makes it more
challenging the second thing that in a
Gena of model we should have is the Gena
of model has a belief about how the
world causes its
Sensations namely if the world is at any
given state that by my estimation beyond
my Markov blanket what is the most
likely sensation why that I will be
experiencing right so these two are the
key components of a generative model so
like mathematically this is how you show
it x dot is literally the velocity of uh
the world how fast it's changing
mathematically it's just DX over DT and
then you have some function of the
states X and causes new and Theta the
parameters of my generative model plus
some random fluctuation Omega X so that
equation is called a state Dynamics
equation but what it basically is
telling you is that the Dynamics of the
world is driven by X by the position of
the world basically and these are all my
belief about how the world is changing
DX over DT the velocity of the
world and technically speaking f is
called the flow of the state Dynamics
it's the deterministic part of the state
Dynamics Omega X random fluctuation is
what encodes your un certainty about
your belief about how the world is
changing yeah the second equation uh
basically connects to the second concept
that I introduced here it's basically
telling you that my belief about my
sensation about like what's the most
likely um Sensation that I'm going to be
receiving is encoded in this equation
where my
observation is equal to the G of the
function of again
hidden States the causes new and the
parameters some parameters plus some
random fluctuation Omega y it's called
the observation model again Omega y
encodes your uncertainty about your
belief about the most likely Sensation
that you will be experiencing a
sensation that is caused by the world
you notice that we have this these again
your hidden saer X and then uh the cause
is new now if you're wondering so
you know what the thetas are these are
just the parameters of the functional
form of FNG G but if you're wondering
what causes are this is something that
I'm not going to be focusing in this um
particular talk but just imagine that if
you have a hierarchical generative model
these causes are just a subset of the
Hidden States these are like the hidden
states that do not have Dynamics but
they're the tools that different levels
in the hierarchy use to be able to talk
to each other so interlayer
communication is done using these news
or the
causes these are the ones that basically
Drive the Dynamics you notice that
that's why we have x. equals f of x and
new they they drive they drive the
Dynamics without them the layers cannot
talk to each other
basically now if you want to like turn
this into a belief-based
system where you have probabilities in
play you you just need to assume a
gussan distribution over your random
fluctuation namely with mean mean zero
and some Precision uh over your random
variable X and your observation y just
my you know Open brackets Precision is
just inverse
uncertainty um and close brackets that's
just a notion in
statistics Now using this if you
literally replace um you know this um
notion of a Galan distribution into
your original equation you end up with
this probabilistic sort of um uh you
know notion that the probability of X do
given all of these three
elements is distributed according to our
normal distribution where again the
Precision is the same as the Precision
of your random fluctuation but you
notice that because we're summing up f
with this guy over here the the mean of
that Gan distribution becomes this F
term same story for the your belief
about your why your your observations
and that is why I'm saying that f of x
and new and Theta is the expected your
expected um Dynamics about X do because
it's literally the expected value of the
gussian distribution same story here G
of X new and Theta is your expectation
about your observation your sensation
again it is the sort of expected value
of this gussan distribution the value
that is most likely to occur
so that's generative model two things we
know the Dynamics of the world we have
beliefs let's say we don't know it we
have beliefs about the Dynamics of the
world and we have belief about uh
basically the most likely Sensation that
we will be experiencing if such and such
was the State of Affair of the world
let's say x was the State of Affairs in
the
world now we talked about inference
let's talk about Bas rule really quickly
now here this is base Rule and the
components of Base rule are as follows
we have the likelihood term which is the
probability of my observation given uh
the state of the world we have a prior
belief which means that before observing
why this is my belief about what the
world looks like we have the model
evidence which is probability of data
and these two together is called
basically the the generative model again
like this is in line with what what we
discussed here this is basically your
prior belief about the Dynamics and this
is literally the mapping between X and Y
which is your likelihood term so I'm not
saying anything new here these two
together are your generative model and
this is your model evidence this is a
devil right this is intractable you
notice that in a real life scenario we
will not be able to calculate this and
this term on the left hand side is
called posterior probability it's your
belief about the distribution over
hidden state of the world
X and when you map your generative model
using base rule to uh this posterior
distribution we call this model
inversion right so if whenever you hear
model inversion in the context of FP
that's what we mean by
that so this evidence again going back
to our idea of marginalizing a variable
out if you again just remind yourself
that this is how you marginalize the
hidden State hit or X out you just end
up with probability of let's say
sensation why you notice that this
integration could get really nasty
really fast which means that if you have
you you could have basically any number
of hidden States X and for each X you
would have a range of possible values so
this thing could turn into a potentially
like potentially in infinite number of
nested integrals basically it can it can
become intractable really really quickly
so what this means is we will not be
able to calculate this posterior
probability um exactly so what should we
do the answer is variational
inference so because U you you see
probability of data your model evidence
is intractable but at the same time
ironically it's the true measure of how
good your generative model is um which
means that we call this also marginal
likelihood right so if it is high it
means
whatever sensation you're experiencing
right now under your model of the world
under your generative model of the world
the probability of that particular
sensation is very high it means under
your model of the world everything that
you're sensing you already expected to
to sense it so it means you have such a
strong and uh you know and precise
belief and precise yeah belief about the
Dynamics of the world and how the
sensations are generated from those uh
those dynamics that whatever you're
receiving is not surprising that that's
why model evidence is such a strong
metric for evaluating how good a
generative model is but unfortunately
it's intractable so can we find a bound
to this namely a lower bound and the
answer is yes I'm going to introduce the
idea of a evidence lower bound and the
next slide so by doing this I'm turning
the problem on its head so I'm turning a
converting let's say a an intractable
exact calculation of the
posterior and I'm replacing that with a
tractable
approximation um well basically a
tractable approximate estimation of the
posterior and that's called variational
inference and I'll tell you what why we
call this variational by the way because
the objective function that we're going
to be minimizing to do that is VAR free
energy is actually a function of a
function it's a functional so where
wherever you're dealing with functionals
and optimizing functionals U that's
where the calculus of variation comes
into play that's what what it means by
variational
inference now on the right hand side I'm
just going to put some reminders the
expected value and the this particular
particular law of logarithms and in the
middle this is called genon inequality
just keep keep them keep an eye on this
one it just says that the expected value
of a log of something is always a lower
bound to the log of the expected value
of that thing right so this is going to
come in handy so
let's study the this U amazing concept
of evidence lower bound remember P of Y
is intractable we want to find the bound
to
it so this is log of probability of data
um this is how we mark marginalized X
out and you can multiply and divide by
this by by by something right whatever
it is so here QX is we call this
surrogate the surrogate posterior over
the hidden State this is going to be a
representative or your approximation to
the true unknown posterior belief right
so let's call it QX and it's by the way
it's really a key factor in variational
inference and Fe so keep that in mind
this Q um um variable this Q
function so moving on you you do a
little bit of play here so this this
sort of Cu moves to the denominator and
you notice that this is the definition
of expectation with respect to this
particular distribution Q right just
getting the definition from uh from
here and according to jens's
inequality um this term has a lower B
and this is the lower bound to it so the
expected of of this term the expected
value of this term over this probability
distribution you have the joint here and
you have the surrogate distribution here
and you see so this right hand side
again remind yourself this is your log
model evidence and we found the lower
bound to it using jens's inequality
right so the lower bound is found this
guy is your evidence lower
bound um and that that's a key finding
that by maximizing this evidence lower
band you're actually maximizing uh your
your log model evidence and you're
getting closer and closer to the true
posterior now elbow and vfe just want to
make sure that we're clear on this we
have elbow here um but VF or variational
inference is just negative of your elbow
so if you multiply NE minus one by both
sides of this you end up with this term
always bigger than minus log probability
of data this is called surprisal and
this is called variational fre energy
that's why we say VF is always an upper
bound to surprise so maximizing elbow or
minimizing VF they they both mean the
same
thing and um this is basically called
variational free energy and that's why
we call this a functional because this
thing is a function of a of another
function and this called surprisal or
surprise and just shows you in a plot
that here you've got variational free
energy that's always an upper bound to
the true unknown surprisal or by
extension you got your elbow here that's
always a lower bound to the true um log
model evidence so VF has multiple
incarnations it comes in different form
by playing with the math so if this is
your this is your vfe just expand you
can just expand the joint and the
denominator and then literally use the
log rule of the you know uh the division
turned into the subtraction and then you
can distribute the expectation across
the two different terms and this um this
basically results into like just
basically swapping these two terms uh by
each other you end up with this equation
right and these terms have names so this
one actually this expected value between
your belief about the the hidden State
and the true unknown posterior this
expectation is called a a
a KL Divergence it measures how
different your belief about X QX is from
the true unknown posterior that's why
it's called an approximate error
approximation error and the second term
is your surprise
right um so um if I want to like show
you like what this actually means
visually this is really interesting so
this is your surprisal right and on top
of surprisal you're adding thex imation
error this is this sort of length over
here and then this constitutes your free
energy what this means is like free
energy is always an upper bound on
surprisal and the error the that Gap is
your approximation error is how far your
belief about X is from the true
posterior so by tuning your generative
model your variational free energy goes
down and when it goes down this Gap is
reducing so which means that your Q gets
closer and closer to the true true
posterior which means a better and
better perception about the world and
this doesn't end here your free energy
will get closer and closer to the
surprisal um basically by extension to
the model evidence which is the metric
that we're going to be use using for you
know comparing different models with one
another a second incarnation of vfe is
again we're going to expand the
denominator again into this joint so
previously was P of x given y times
probity of y now we go pro y given x
times P of X and again Distributing um
the log and then we distribute the uh
you know the
expectation and then just you know uh
swapping the terms again you have this
scale Divergence over here and you have
this negative negative expectation now
this thing over here is called accuracy
it means how accurate am I under my
belief of the world the expect the
expected value of observing why under my
estimation of where the world is X so
the higher this is it means the more
accurate your belief about the world is
that is that is basically causing your
observations but at the same time this
term over here is called complexity it
means that if you have some prior belief
about the world you you will not be able
to just move your queue wherever you
want it is it has to stay close to your
prior belief over here so this is
basically a reg regularizer if you
will um and the third
Incarnation is um basically again here
this is the definition of vfe again you
know the log rule um so we end up with
these two terms so this guy over here is
called expected
sorry it's called expected internal
energy and this guy is your entropy so
this the expected value of log of QX we
call this entropy
um how do we minimize raal free energy
we have to maximize our entropy and we
have to maximize our internal energy now
this term makes sense that we need to
maximize it but what does this one mean
it means that your Q will stay as smooth
as possible as simple as possible this
connects really well with aom's Razer if
you're from machine learning background
that your the best model is the one that
provides the most accurate account of
the data but at the same time the
simplest explanation for that data this
Simplicity is enforced by this entropy
term it it states
smooth so this is very interesting so
these were just three incarnations of
variational free energy and the goal of
inverting the generative model is
basically we the GM strives to minimize
this vfe um this achieves two things I
hinted this uh just a little bit
previously but it means that the actual
uh value of VF will approach the
intractable minus log probability of
data this is going to be used for model
comparison and the surrogate
distribution will approach the unknown
posterior belief remember that was the
goal of um you know perception in the
first place and once you reach that
basically minimize your variational free
energy you can use the actual value of
free energy as the metric as a proxy for
the unknown model evidence to compare
different generative models together
right so the model with the lowest
rational free energy is going to be the
best model yeah I think I've explained
that one now just to let you know that
the true form of the posterior is
unknown and you see the the the terms
like the the probability distribution
The Joint distribution here um it is not
guaranteed that um you know they're
analytically simple you know to to
derive and and you know work with
because of that um there is this idea
that we can actually use llas
approximation to break down each one of
the distributions and basically
approximate them using a tailor
expansion um particularly up to the
third term which means that I'm
providing a quadratic approximation
using tailor expansion for each one of
the components um within variational fee
energy um unfortunately I don't have the
time to go over the detailed derivation
but suffice it to say that the result of
you know s approximating all the
components is that the variational free
energy simplifies the dise equation for
those of you who are interested at to
know the details I encourage you to look
at the primer on variational plusus
paper which is an amazing paper um it
goes through all the details of
derivation so basically free energy um
reduces to log of the joint
distribution and you have the posterior
um covariance and then yeah n is
basically the number of parameters and
the states that you have and so on and
so
forth now predictive coding this this is
basically where it gets even more
interesting it is a basically a
hierarchical generative model that we're
going to be using to model human
perception and the goal is to invert
this hierarchical model so it's a
powerful framework to describe how the
cortex accumulates evidence from noisy
stimuli um it's an application of the
free energy principle it focuses on how
this literally fantastic organ can
perform probabilistic inference about
the most likely hidden cause that has
caused the sensory signal um it assumes
that the brain has a generative model of
the world through which it constantly
infers the hidden states of the world
and it can also learn the parameters
while inferring the hidden state of the
world so model inversion happens by
minimizing variational free energy again
even though it's hierarchical but the
concept is stays the same so in
predictive coding we have this concept
of top- down predictions where
predictions go from inside out about
your Sensations right and then the
prediction error is calculated like what
I described before and then this these
errors if I want to be more precise the
Precision weighted prediction errors are
sent back from outside in uh or they
call it some up sort of Direction so
that the the estimations of the world
the estimation of the posterior beliefs
about the world are corrected basically
that's what model inversion that's when
model inversion happens when the
posterior estimates get adjusted and it
looks like something like this we have
this
hierarchical model that we have the same
story of State Dynamics and observation
model but here we have this happening at
each level and then you notice that
these news these causes are the ones
that link layer I to I minus one that's
the important part that without these
news without these causes the layers
cannot talk to each other you notice
that it is a hierarchical dynamical
system uh
basically
um now how do we design an experiment um
for you know for for for this kind of
perception neuromatic modeling using the
free energy principle I just want to
give you the sort of ingredients here
you the designer you first have to
Define your generative process that's X
that's the true uh hidden stat I should
have maybe said xar yeah xstar would
have been a better notion then you will
generate the observations this is some
sort of some transformation of the X's
you can add noise to it you can
transform it the way you want but that's
going to be the observations that's
going to hit the Markov blanket this
these are what this uh this is basically
where the sensory state observ and
receive those
Sensations you have to Define your
generative model this this part is the
tricky part right the fs and G's in your
dynamical system that's where uh
everything gets really tricky how would
you define them if it's hierarchical how
many layers should it have basically
these are the big
questions you have to define the
evaluation metric that how would you
define different Genera of models um
with each other and then you uh you have
to design the online State inference
Loop now this is by the way just for
this case for this presentation is just
about State inference and then you have
to compare different gen of models this
is where beian model comparison comes
into play now here um you basically use
a dynamical system here I'm just using a
lotka voltera process that you know
captures the Dynamics between uh Hunter
and and the prey together it's a
two-dimensional sort of world if you
will so by solving the trajectories by
solving the differential equations you
get to this sort of trajectory so you
have 1,000 data points here each which
is two-dimensional so this is the
unknown states of the world right this
is the unknown dynamics of the world to
gener a
process again it's unknown it's beyond
the mark of
blanket again so this is the figure that
we saw before now you can assume that
you got the brain here and you've got uh
the generative process xstar on the left
hand side the observations why are
basically a noisy version of the same
hidden states that you notice that this
this is really noisy here right so the
brain has to receive that and then infer
the true States here
right so for a one layer predictive
coding Network for these particular
experiments you have just s a simple
sort of generative model it's just one
layer and then uh I'm sort of comparing
two generative models here where the
flow of the of the state Dynamics are
different on the left hand side you have
something that we call just it's just
just a pullback attractor uh we have
this 2 by two Matrix here and we have
this sort of point of Attraction which
assumes that everything collapses into
this world just just to be clear it
means that my generative model of the
world assumes that the world Beyond The
Mark of blanket is attracted to a
particular Center called saigh right
that's what I mean by believing
something about the world whereas the
second flow the second generative model
is a sinusoidal sort of belief it means
that I believe there is something
periodic about the world beyond my
Markov blanket and the G's I just kept
them as identity which means that
whatever new is is going to be my
prediction about my sensation right so I
kept the G's identical now the
evaluation metric this is very
important as the inference is happening
online for every observation you have to
make an inference um and then predict
the sensation and then calculate the
prediction error and then eventually
calculate variational free energy
because it's happening online you can
actually literally accumulate your free
energy variational free energy across
the entire inference period so at the
end you will end up with one scalar
value it's called the time integral of
of your variational free energy they
call it free action right it's just a
fancy way of summing up variational free
energy across the entire infer inference
period in basically it's time
integral and it is
it's an upper bound to the accumulated
surprise so variational free energy is
an upper bound to surprise and um free
action is an is an upper bound to the
accumulat surprise because free action
is in and out of itself an accumulation
of variational free energy and this is
you have to also then Define the online
State inference Loop uh I don't want to
go into too much detail here but um
basically for each observation you will
make predictions and you Cal the
prediction errors you calculate your
free energy you calculate the gradient
of free energy with respect to your
estimations of the posterior that's the
key part and then this is where you have
to update your beliefs about the world
and you notice you notice that it's a
differential equation because the way
you're going to update your um your
belief about the world it's
continuous it happens in continuous time
it means between each two observations
Yi and Yi + one I have to integrate over
this update rule to move from my
previous belief about the world mux to a
new mux at the next time step and that's
why the integration happens here and
just so you know this equation is
basically saying that the amount by
which I'm going to change my belief
about the world mux is first of all the
gradient of free energy with respect to
mux right that's typical gradient
descent but the second term it serves as
a momentum it means that if I'm going to
update my belief about where the world
is I'm going to consider the velocity of
the world as well right if I'm going to
estimate the velocity of the world I'm
going to consider the acceleration of
the world as well it's it's similar to
the idea of momentum in optimization
algorithms this is the bit that helps
you you know catch up with the chasing
Target that is the world that I talked
about in the beginning and then by you
integrate this differential equation to
to update your belief about the world
and then the next observation happens so
this continues for all the observations
and you're accumulating your free energy
as time goes by and the result will be
your ve your free action so the result
is this so this is the first generative
model with the pullback
attractor um so this is the uh infert
state right and this is the this is
interesting this is the accumulated free
action right um very very interesting
you notice that free action um is having
these regular jumps it means
periodically I'm getting surprised about
my Sensations remember that if you note
here the this is where these
nonlinearities happen it means that my
simple pullback attractor fails to
capture those Dynamics so it gets
surprise but interestingly where things
are linear and simple I'm not getting
much surprise so it's almost constant
here so I'm good at capturing simple
Dynamics but not highly not the ones
that are nonlinear whereas the
sinusoidal one you notice that we are
capturing the magnitudes much better we
have a steady increase in free action we
don't get surprise for some Dynamics and
less surprise for other Dynamics we are
always equally surprised for everything
which is interesting that like here we
are getting surprised consistently for
everything but here we are not getting
much surprise for these particular
Dynamics so one is good Capt good in
capturing nonlinear Dynamics periodic
Dynamics the other one is better in
capturing simpler linear Dynamics which
is interesting and notice that the
reaction here is much lower than the
freeaction here so basically this means
that this model is much better now
looking at the Gen the generative power
of these uh GMS so this is the G
function if you remember G of X and mu
that's the prediction of your one layer
predictive coding Network about the
sensation that's the bit that gets
compared with the true sensation and the
prediction error is calculated remember
that observations just like hden say are
two-dimensional so this is the first
dimension of why the true sensation and
why had the predicted sensation you
notice that they're almost close and
also with the second um Dimension they
it's not doing a bad job right but for
the second generative model again it's
doing a much better job in capturing the
magnitudes of this of the system again
you notice that it's not so good in
generating these bits whereas this the
first model is better in generating
prediction more accurate predictions of
the of the first
St now these are the results the
pullback attractor and trigonometric the
sinos soidal um sort of flow you notice
that the freeaction of the second model
is lower it's better and M loss which
basically comp uh compares the estimated
X and the true X the inferred X and true
X together is is also slightly lower so
free action shows that the second model
is good and this is where beijia model
comparison uh comes into play where we
use base factor for comparison it
basically says that we take the the
model evidence for each one of the
models and we divide them now because
these are intractable we're using free
action as a proxy and when you put the
values of free action you get to this
value because it's higher than one it
basically means that you have to pick
the second model because it has a lower
free action it doesn't get as surprised
as the first one and at some point of
caution free action versus MSE MSE as a
measure of accuracy should never and I
repeat never be consulted on its own
because it ignores complexity so for
example what if the freeaction of model
one and model two the model one had a
lower freeaction but what if the MSE of
the first model was actually higher than
M than the second model which one would
you choose again you have to choose
model one because this has higher power
of generalizability to the Unseen data
so it has less chances of overfitting to
the data we call that free action again
as complexity minus accuracy so what if
we remove complexity again we will
overfit but that was important some
final thoughts you can definitely learn
the parameters and also estimate
uncertainty about the world so these are
the things that are not covered in this
presentation but you can do that this is
where the separation of time scales um
will come into play the demm algorithm
does exactly that this is dynamic
expectation maximization I encourage you
guys to take a look at that algorithm
it's you using that you can solve the
triple estimation
problem now can I go beyond x dot yes
you can that's where you jump into the
world of the generalized coordinates of
motion where you're not only using X
estimating X do but you're also
estimating higher temporal derivatives
of uh of the world you have a a system
of couple differential equations rather
than having just two equations which is
very very interesting
actually um also remember that active
inference is not the same as predictive
coding um particularly in the philosophy
um you know um communities I've heard
that people use active inference when
they're talking about predictive coding
remember that in predictive coding we
are simply doing um making sense of the
world there is no concept of planning or
action in play um the ml Community
unfortunately um does not work with the
Dynamics of the world and AI uh um
basically is going to the opposite
direction instead of uh using smart data
we're just going bigger and bigger data
so we would like a world that chat GPT
would also ask you a question and
becomes curious about you to to receive
information that it selects basically so
where should you start with with the
free energy principle these are the
resources that I strongly recommend you
some videos on YouTube hopefully you can
later on pause this video and go through
these links some papers that I'm
recommending here and the last one the
two books that I believe the red one the
predictive minus for philosophy
community and the first one goes through
the math extensively it's a beautiful uh
book yeah the uh and the videos I I I
recommend that you guys start with the
videos in the first place and I would
like to just acknowledge our funding
from the maryury and also my colleagues
Simon bbus and professor priston and
also acknowledge the folks that UCL UC
UCD and monach University who have
always supported uh uh our work and
here's the link to the the code that
everybody can just take a look and run
the read me file is self-explanatory
unfortunately I ran out of time and I
won't be able to show a demo but yeah
that's it so thank you Maron that was
great and and uh we have 10 minutes if
you want to show anything or I can ask
some questions but but we have till five
minutes after if you want to show
anything or even just scanning the repo
could be cool okay sure sure sure that's
great thank you for that but just wanted
to comment your your educational
material and the YouTube channel are
great and and they are they're an
excellent supplement to the textbook and
to the math
learning I appreciate that yes um
absolutely uh so yeah I also have a
YouTube channel mlon feel free to take a
look I'm actually reading the active
inference book on that channel so
hopefully it would be of interest to you
guys and this is the repository that is
publicly available um the read me file
is pretty self-explanatory and this is
just a one predictive coding Network for
the task of inference and modeling human
perception as a task of inference these
are the same pluss that you've seen um
so basically all the functions are here
right everything you need is here so the
main function is the one that you're
going to be dealing with and the yaml
file is where you actually choose the
parameters uh of your experiment just to
show you in action what it looks like so
if you actually clone this repository on
your machine you just have to go to the
yaml file and just do a quick scan of
the readme file but basically uh using
this is where you define your generative
process for example you can say I want
it to be a lotka vola process and this
is how I'm going to be picking the DT
and the total time uh to actually solve
the trajectories of my generative
process you can Define your generative
model here you can Define the Dynamics
to be like a pullback attractor or a
trigonometric one the likelihood for
example is identity here these are the
dimensions of your X and Y two and one
you might wonder why it's two for X is
because you have x and x dot together
where the world is and how fast the
world is changing and this is just Why
in your generative model you can
increase them uh that's where you jump
into the world of generalized
coordinates of motion but this is beyond
the scope of my talk today again this
these bits are beyond the the scope of
our talk today this is where uh you
basically C talk about the correlation
between the noise process across
different levels of the generalized
coordinates so the noise on the velocity
how does it correlate with the noise
process on the acceleration your belief
about the acceleration of the world so
how do they interact with one another
that's where these um values come into
play and then this is the kind of noise
that you will use to alter the true
states of the world and generate your
observations for example you can use a
colored noise here you define the mean
and uh basically the standard deviation
of noise and this is we're using the
sort of Kernel here that convolves with
the white noise to actually generate a
more smooth noise the reason being that
um the biological systems are believed
to be uh working with uh you know to so
all all the signals that you work with
in biological and organic systems are
believed to have been generated by some
sort of dynamics that that's why we keep
them as smooth noises infinitely
differentiable noises rather than just
white
noise and uh if you actually run this so
this is basically a pullback attractor
this is the first uh sort of generative
model that we worked in so you just run
this main
function so we have 1,000 observations
noisy observations right
and immediately this happens so for
every 10 observations we are
accumulating free action you notice that
free action is ever increasing because
it just accumulates free energy and on
the right hand side you have VF or
variational free energy um again if you
look at the definitions inside uh the
functions folder of how we calculate or
compute varation of free energy you
notice that um it's a far more simp
simplified version of what you would see
about energy is because everything is
under llas approximation and you end up
with far more simpler terms and the
final result is reaction is this much
and basically your final MSE loss is0 53
and if you want to see the final output
you just have to go into the results
folder and these are the folders that
are generated just so that you have two
dimensions in x one dimension in y lot
voltera is a generative process for
example do generative model follows a
pullback attractor scheme and then your
G is just identity this is your free
action and then that is your Ms Loss and
if you open it all the plots that I
showed you in the presentation are saved
as PDF here just to give you an idea
like this is your X this is your true
invisible uh states of the world right
and if you want to look at exat this is
the inferred states of the world and
these are for example the the noisy
observations of the world yeah so I hope
that the repository would be um of help
and of interest to all of you thank you
very
much great what kinds of problems or
settings do you feel that this could be
adapted to or useful
for um I would say first foremost this
could be used for um basically it's it's
all about any kind of problem that's
about inference you have some noisy
observations that you want to infer the
hidden state but in terms of
adaptability you can build on that by
introducing parameter learning as well
as uncertainty estimation so our goal is
to develop this into a triple estimation
sort of package predictive coding
Network and add more layers to it so to
have a hierarchical predictive coding uh
capable of solving the triple estimation
problem yeah that's the ultimate thing
that you can actually adapt this
to
cool
um what are your uh what are you excited
about for ML Dawn or for your learning
or research in next
year um I'm very much excited in
embedding these kinds of calculations
into the world of AI because as I said
AI is moving in my opinion and my humble
opinion is moving to the towards a wrong
direction instead of bombarding models
with all sorts of data that the model
should be able to choose its data so I'm
very excited in you know developing this
framework into a hierarchical predictive
coding Network and then sort of compare
the performance of such a model with
other traditional aib based generative
models and basically show its
superiority um that I believe it has in
different scenarios and ultimately this
model is going to be used for in my
grant proposal and a project I'm working
on is going to be used for modeling
hallucinations as a kind of false
inference about the world um and it's
going to be used as a proxy to for us to
understand what happens in uh
Neuropsychiatric disorders when people
actually suffer from hallucinations in
the brain so this predictive coding
network is going to be a brain inspired
AI model for us to understand what goes
wrong in in the skull of a human being
when they suffer from hallucinations
about the world so that's what I'm
really really excited about and really
hoping to achieve cool it's like
inspired by the brain for the
brain absolutely thank youon great great
presentation and good luck with the
continuation of the work appreciate it
thank you for having me okay till next
time e